RONNY NGUYEN

LIGO SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATION



2089 Rehoboth Rd. Ext. Bowman, GA, 30624



nguryu@protonmail.com

SUMMARY

I am a recent bachelor's student of physics from the University of New Hampshire (UNH). Since 2017, I have been engaged in research in experimental gravitation, numerical relativity, and high-energy astronomy at UNH, NASA, and Cardiff University accumulating in 4 years of research experience. I have been a member of various research groups ranging from small teams to international collaborations.

Outside of research, I enjoy challenging myself physically and mentally by hiking in the mountains of New England, farming, and reading philosophy.

PROGRAMMING

Python

MATLAB

С

Bash

Git

FINESSE

SKILLS

High Performance Computing

Parallel Computing

Machine Learning & Neural Networks

Signal Processing

Parameter Estimation

Physics Simulation

Mathematical Modeling

Laser Interferometry

Scientific Writing

Science Communication

Research Collaboration

Teaching

EDUCATION

Aug. 2015 May 2019 B.S. PHYSICS, MINOR PHILOSOPHY, GPA: 3.5 UNIVERSITY OF NEW HAMPSHIRE – DURHAM, US

EXPERIENCE

Sep. 2020 Present

LIGO SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATION, CARDIFF, UK RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Research assistant at Cardiff University doing research with the LIGO Scientific Collaboration in gravitational waves.

- Collaborated internationally with researchers at University of Texas at Austin and Cardiff University.
- Applied Bayesian parameter estimation algorithms to infer the parameters of gravitational wave sources.
- Utilized parallel computing via the LIGO Data Grid to process 3000+ numerical simulations of black hole mergers.
- Simulated tabletop laser interferometers using the FINESSE Python library.
- Tested a neural network to perform likelihood-free inference of the parameters of gravitational wave events.

Jun. 2020 Aug. 2020

NASA MARSHALL SPACE FLIGHT CENTER, HUNTSVILLE, AL SUMMER RESEARCH STUDENT

Intern working with the Fermi-GBM collaboration doing research in gamma-ray bursts.

- Performed systems analysis by calibrating Python data tool parameters for the Fermi-GBM space-based mission based on satellite geometry.
- Wrote Python code to search through the Fermi and Swift gamma-ray catalogs.
- Used NASA data tools to analyze each gamma-ray event to produce signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) graphs, waterfall likelihood ratio plots, and sky localization maps.

Jun. 2019 Aug. 2019

<u>INTERNSHIP</u>

Intern for the Fermi-GBM collaboration with Dr. Tyson Littenberg's research group doing research in gravitational wave astronomy.

- Worked on the development of space-based gravitational wave mission, LISA (Laser Interferometer Space Antenna).
- Analyzed astrophysical noise received by LISA using Bayesian inference and Fourier analysis.
- Presented poster of findings for the intern PosterExpo.

COURSEWORK

ONLINE

MITLL - Intro. to Radar Systems

MITLL – Adaptive Antennas and Phased Arrays

PHYSICS

General Physics I, II & III

Classical Mechanics I & II

Experimental Physics I & II

Quantum Mechanics I & II

Electromagnetism I & II

Thermodynamics and Stat. Mech.

General Relativity and Cosmology

Nuclear Physics

Experimental Gravitation I & II

Advanced Research Methods I & II

Data Analysis

Numerical Relativity and Waveforms

Gravitational Wave Astrophysics

MATHEMATICS

Calculus I & II

Multidimensional Calculus

Differential Equations

Linear Algebra with Applications

HONORS

US-UK Fulbright Alternate Candidate
UNH Honors Scholar
Sigma Pi Sigma Physics Honors

Sep. 2017 May 2019

UNIVERSITY OF NEW HAMPSHIRE, DURHAM, NH RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Research assistant working with Dr. Francois Foucart's research group doing research in numerical relativity.

- Tested numerical simulations of binary neutron star mergers (~6.5 million particles) using on the Trillian and Blue Waters supercomputing clusters.
- Performed data analysis on neutrino radiation transport from a binary neutron star merger that used a Monte-Carlo algorithm.
- Modeled the matter outflow of particles from a binary neutron star merger to study the time evolution of the system.

May 2017 May 2019

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Research assistant working with Dr. Dacheng Lin at the UNH Space Science Center doing research in X-ray astronomy.

- Updated the XMM-Newton space observatory X-ray catalog funded by NASA grant #NNX17AJ57G.
- Performed data analysis using Python on 30,000+ X-ray sources to analyze lightcurves and SNR graphs.
- Collaborated in writing the scientific paper to accompany the updated catalog.

Aug. 2016 Dec. 2018

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Teaching assistant for studio physics I, and general physics I at the UNH Department of Physics.

- Coordinated peer-based group work in a classroom of 40 students (10 groups of 4).
- Aided in problem solving strategies, and explained fundamental principles in calculus based physics in a studio environment.
- Instructed lab sessions that were integrated into the course and introduced students to LaTeX and Python.

Ronny Nguyen

Address: 2089 Rehoboth Road Ext., Bowman GA, 30624

Phone: (603) 858-4749

Email: nguryu@protonmail.com

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/nguryu

EDUCATION

Aug. 2015 – May 2019 B.S. Physics, University of New Hampshire (UNH)

Minor in Philosophy

Thesis: Determination of Multi-messenger Signals from Matter Outflows

of Merger Systems Advisor: Francois Foucart

RESEARCH

Research areas Experimental gravitation, high-energy astronomy, theoretical

astrophysics

Publications

In progress Parameter Estimation of Intermediate-mass Black Hole Candidates with

RIFT

R. Nguyen, J. Lange

Jan. 2021 Extracting the Parameters of GW190519 with RIFT

R. Nguyen, J. Lange, V. Raymond

Jun. 2018 Evaluating radiation transport errors in merger simulations using a

Monte-Carlo algorithm

F. Foucart, M.D. Duez, L.E. Kidder, R. Nguyen, H.P. Pfeiffer, M.A.

Scheel

Presentations

Nov. 2019 Poster – A Study of Matter Outflows from a Binary Neutron Star Merger

The New Faces of Black Holes Conference, Annapolis, Maryland

Apr. 2019 Poster – A Study of Matter Outflows from a Binary Neutron Star Merger

UNH Undergraduate Research Conference, Durham, New Hampshire

Apr. 2018 Poster – X-ray Sources from XMM-Newton and the Search for Tidal

Disruption Events

UNH Undergraduate Research Conference, Durham, New Hampshire

WORK EXPERIENCE

Sep. 2020 – Present Research Assistant/LIGO Scientific Collaboration member

Cardiff University/UT Austin

Principle Investigator(s): Vivien Raymond, Jacob Lange

Jun. 2020 – Sep. 2020 – Summer Research Student

NASA Marshall Space Flight Center

Principle Investigator: Colleen Wilson-Hodge

Aug. 2019 – Dec. 2019 – Adjunct Researcher

UNH Department of Physics

Principle Investigator: Francois Foucart

Jun. 2019 – Aug. 2019 Internship

NASA Marshall Space Flight Center

Advisor(s): Tyson Littenberg, Colleen Wilson-Hodge

Sep. 2017 – Jun. 2019 Research Assistant

UNH Department of Physics

Principle Investigator: Francois Foucart

May 2017 - Jun. 2019 Research Assistant

UNH Space Science Center

Principle Investigator: Dacheng Lin

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Python, C, Git and Github, bash, MATLAB, FINESSE, High

performance computing, Parallel computing

Laboratory Interferometer design and operation, NMR techniques, Nuclear

spectroscopy

Data Analysis Bayesian inference, Signal processing, Machine learning, Markov-Chain

Monte-Carlo, Physics simulation, Mathematical modeling

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Aug. 2019 - Dec. 2019 Tutor | PHYS 508 - Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics

UNH Department of Physics

Jan. 2019 – May 2019 — Teaching Assistant | MATH 645 – Linear Algebra for Applications

UNH Department of Mathematics

Aug. 2016 - Dec. 2018 Teaching Assistant | PHYS 407S - Studio Physics I, PHYS 407 -

General Physics I

UNH Department of Physics

OUTREACH

Nov. 2019	Public talk – LISA Ambassadors Listening to the Universe presentation at Oyster River High School
Oct. 2019	Public talk – LISA Ambassadors Listening to the Universe presentation at Somersworth High School

HONORS & AWARDS

Apr. 2020 US-UK Fulbright alternate candidate

Jan. 2016 – May 2019 – UNH Honors Program scholar

May 2018 Sigma Pi Sigma physics honors society member